Guide to the H.K. Hathaway Papers, 1907-1929 JL011
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
H.K. Hathaway Papers,
1907-1929
JL011
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
12.0 Linear feet
Hathaway, H. King
Scope and Content
Collection consists of reports and correspondence concerning the reorganization of various companies that consulted Hathaway, a prominent management consultant, mainly in the East and New England, but in several cases in San Francisco. The years covered are 1907 to 1929, with the exception of two books presented to the business school in 1937, containing scientific management material. These papers consist of both incoming and outgoing correspondence pertaining to the reports compiled by Hathaway, and the reports themselves.
Material on machine operations and various industrial information comprise the rest of the collection. These instruction cards and abstract management reports (that is, not pertaining to a specific company) cover the years 1922-1924, approximately.
H. King Hathaway was a consulting engineer in New York and San Francisco, associated with the Schlage Lock Company in San Francisco, and the Tabor Manufacturing Company of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He was a principal follower of Frederick W. Taylor, the “Father of Scientific Management”, and there are several documents related to Taylor in this collection.
Provenance
Gift of H. King Hathaway to the Jackson Library of Business. Transferred to the Department of Special Collections in 1979.
Access Restrictions
None.
- REPORTS AND CORRESPONDENCE REGARDING COMPANIES CONSULTED AND EXAMINED BY HATHAWAY
  - Acme Wire Company, New Haven, Conn., 1911-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arkell Safety Bag Company, New York, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beech-Nut Packing Company, Canajoharie, New Jersey, 1907-1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beech-Nut Packing Company, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bethleham Shipbuilding Corporation, South Bethleham, Pennsylvania, March-Oct 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bethleham Shipbuilding Corp., Nov 1919-Feb 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bethleham Shipbuilding Corp. (data), 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bethleham Shipbuilding Corp. (data, charts), 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bethleham Shipbuilding Corp. (foundry reports), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Barcalo Manufacturing Company, Buffalo, N.Y., 1912-Dec 1913 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Barcalo Mfg. Co., Jan 1914-Jan 1917 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brockton Heel Company, Campello, Mass., 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Day and Zimmerman and Penn Central Light and Power Company, Philadelphia, Pa., 1907-1913 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Day and Zimmerman and Penn Central, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Day and Zimmerman and Penn Central, (misc. reports), 1913 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Delong Hook and Eye Company, Philadelphia, 1919-1921 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Eaton, Crane & Pike Company, Pittsfield, Mass., 1913-1920 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Eaton, Crane & Pike Co., 1920-1923 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hermann-Aukam & Company, New York, 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hermann-Aukam & Company, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Company, Pittsburg, Pa. (Box 4, Folder 21-24)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Company, 1920-1924 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - The Plimpton Press, Norwood, Mase., 1908-1916 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - J.C. Plimpton & Company, Liverpool, England (data) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - J.C. Plimpton & Company, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Plymouth Cordage Works, No. Plymouth, Mass., 1911 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Plymouth Cordage Works, 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Sanford E. Thompson, Boston, Mass., 1910-1917 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - National Magnesia Manufacturing Company (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Marchant Calculating Machine Company, San Francisco, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - New England Butt Company, Providence, R.I., 1912-1920 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Milbrook's Restaurant, New York (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Department of Education, San Francisco, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - United Gas Improvement Company, Philadelphia, Pa., 1911-1923 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - United States Cast Iron Pipe and Foundry, Burlington, Jew Jersey, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Lovell-McConnell Manufacturing Co., Newark, N.J., 1911 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - C. Stanley Hurlbut, Philadelphia, Pa., 1919 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Farrel Foundry and Machine Co., Ansoma, Conn., 1911-1912 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - H.C. Cohn Co., Rochester, N.Y., 1919-1923 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Commercial Truck Co. of America, Phil., Pa., 1916 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - George W. Smith & Co., 1919 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Roland Park Co., Baltimore, Md., 1912 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Roentgen Manufacturing Co., Phil., Pa., 1912 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Republic Metalware Co., Buffalo, N.Y., 1913 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - New York Shipbuilding Corp., 1922 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - J.H. Williams & Co., Buffalo, N.Y., 1916 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Marcel Michelin, Clermont, France, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Gulf District Statistics (Box 7, Folder 51a)
  - Chemical Works (Box 7, Folder 51b)
- TABOR MANUFACTURING COMPANY (Philadelphia)
  - Forms (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Forms (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Exhibits (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Instruction cards and tool lists (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Cutting speeds for different kinds of metal; photographs of machines. (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Instructions for operating 8" Tabor Mfg. Co. power squeezer; instructions to card writers (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Taylor System Elementary Unit Time DATA SHEETS (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Blue-prints: (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - a) Boxes for “T” Head bolts
    - b) Trays for Taylor's Flying Machine
    - c) Time card and stores issue sorting apparatus-Flying Machine
    - d) Time card racks
    - e) Paring tools
    - f) Round nose roughing tools
    - g) U.S. War Dept. Ordnance Dept. Supply Division; instruction chart for balance of stores sheet-, 1918
    - h) Planning department desk
  - Forging equipment for Taylor standard lathe and planer tools (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Charts: (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - a) Speeds and feeds for machine tools
    - b) Speeds and feeds for machine tools
    - c) Route sheet for handkerchief finishing
    - d) Instruction card and time studies on washing factory windows.
  - Forging instructions and equipment for paring tools (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Same (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Stores system including classification A:S.M.E. (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - a) The care of belting in accordance with the Taylor system. (Box 10)
    - b) Charge symbol classification
    - c) Specifications for High Speed steel cutters for Taylor-Newbold saws and milling cutters
    - d) Examination of drawings
    - e) Entering machine time on cost sheet
    - f) Approval of bills by the auditor
    - g) Conditions governing bonus to be paid on different functions
    - h) Bonus for new men
    - i) Routine and bonus for time clerk
    - j) Bonus specifications for time study man
    - k) Bonus for time study clerk
    - l) Cleaning machines- Bonus time for same
    - m) Standing order for a speed boss
    - n) Duties of the repair boss
    - o) Duties of gang boss
    - p) Duties of an erecting gang boss
    - q) Standing order B.D. Draughting dept. practice and standards
    - r) Order of work for B.D.
    - s) Furnace equipment assignment of men and work
    - t) Standing order for foundry clerk
    - u) Supplement to foundry routine
    - v) (Sales)- follow up system
    - w) The follow up clerk's routine
    - x) Standing orders for entry clerks (per unit)
    - y) Distribution of “overhead” or indirect expenses
    - z) Damage reports
    - a1) Production clerk-location and number of fire pails
    - b1) Standing order for making, issue and recall of tool lists and instruction cards, and issue and recall of tools
    - c1) Standing order for the issue and recall of instruction cards, tool lists, and drawings by the planning dept.
    - d1) Departmental charges
    - e1) Classification of tools
    - a) Classification of worked materials-Sales (Box 11)
    - b) Classification of stores - Sales
    - c) Transcripts of forms- War dept.
- JONES AND LAUGHLIN STEEL CORPORATION (Pittsburg, Pennsylvania)
  - a) Forms (Box 12)
  - b) Small tool data sheets and progress sheets
  - c) Instruction cards under product symbol VB, VC
  - d) Instruction cards under product symbol VF, VG
  - e) Instruction cards under product symbol VH, VJ, VK
  - f) Instruction cards under product symbol VL, VN
  - g) Instruction cards under product symbol VP
  - h) Instruction cards under product symbol VS, VT
  - a) Instruction cards under product symbol VU (Box 13)
  - b) Instruction cards under product symbol VW, VY, VZ
  - c) Index to instruc. cards filed under product symbols VB-VG
  - d) Index to instruc. cards filed under product symbols VH-VP
  - e) Index to instruc. cards filed under product symbols VS-VZ
  - f) Index to instruc. cards covering jobs filed under machine tool symbols
  - g) Instruction cards on grinding
  - h) Instruction cards on grinding
  - i) Instruc. cards covering jobs on horizontal and vertical boring machines, centering machines, etc.
  - j) Standing order on instruc. cards for all machine shop cleaning, July 1922
  - k) Same
  - l) Instruc. cards- miscellaneous, 1923-1924
  - a) Organizations and methods department forms (Box 14)
  - b) Engineering department forms
  - c) Standing order of the general procedure-task and bonus system, 1923
  - d) Standing order on the procedure for inspection of machine operations
  - e) Standing order on various bonus applications
  - f) Standing order of procedure- file and printing branch of the engineering dept.
  - g) Standing order of the procedure-engineering and drawing division of the engineering dept.
  - h) Same
  - i) Engineering and drawing division outline
  - j) Engineering and drawing division and its functions
  - k) Standing order on general procedure of brass foundry
  - l) Procedure for control of operation-No. 2 iron foundry
  - m) (part of) F.W. Taylor Specifications for High Speed Steel
  - n) F.W. Taylor Specifications for High Speed Steel and instruction cards.
  - o) Same
  - p) Same
  - q) Data on standard time records, cutting speeds, etc.
  - r) Maintenance section for No. 1 mill
  - s) Classification of work in fitting section for time study
  - t) Feed and speed and capacity data sheets
  - Feed and Speed and Capacity data sheets (Box 15)
  - Feed and Speed and Capacity data sheets (Box 16)
    - a) Classification sheets taken from small tools classification
    - b) Classification sheets taken from the machine tool classification
    - c) Machine shop belt classification
    - d) Classification sheets taken from machine shop belting classification
    - e) Classification sheets taken from crane classification
    - f) Stores-purchased material
    - g) Classification sheets taken from stores classification- material purchased
    - h) Classification sheets taken from stores classification (worked material-for parts)
    - a) Notebook-workers and hours-steel foundry (Box 17)
    - b) Small tool classification A-DB
    - c) Small tool classification DC-HY
    - d) Small tool classification J-PH
    - a) Small tool classification PL-WZ (Box 18)
    - b) Notebook-machine tool classification
    - c) Notebook-worked materials-classification of parts
    - d) Link Belt Engineering Co.- blueprints
- MISCELLANEOUS REPORTS, PAPERS, SPEECHES, OF F.W. TAYLOR, H.K. HATHAWAY, AND CARL G. BARTH
  - a) Bethleham classification (Box 19)
  - b) Bethleham classification
  - c) Bethleham classification
  - d) Backstrom Report- industrial conditions in U.S.A. Stern Backstrom, 1920.
  - e) Scientific Management Manuscripts
  - f) Sales planning and control- follow up system
  - g) Maintenance of machinery and equipment as a part of the Taylor System of Management
  - h) Same
  - i) The Attitude of Labor Towards Scientific Management-Godfrey Hollis
  - Reports: (Box 20, Folder 66)
    - a) Maintenance of Standards-Victor S. Karabasz
    - b) Training and Selection of Workers-?
    - c) On the Index as a factor in industry-John H. Williams
    - d) Power Distribution Costs-Morris Llewellyn Cooke
    - e) Overhead Expense Distribution- Royal R. Keely
  - Hathaway: Manuscripts and notes (Box 20, Folder 67)
  - Hathaway: Pamphlets, articles, papers (Box 20, Folder 68)
  - Barth: Preliminary report to the Pullman Co. (Box 20, Folder 69)
    - Testimony before Commission on Industrial Relations, 1914
    - Several pamphlets by Barth
  - Barth- Supplement to F.W. Taylor's “On the Art of Cutting Metals”. (Box 20, Folder 70)
    - Tables and charts on Taylor's treatise
  - Taylor- Home Classification (Box 20, Folder 71)
    - Magazine articles regarding Taylor
  - Taylor's death-, March 21, 1915 (Box 20, Folder 72)
    - Announcements
    - Correspondence
    - Remarks
    - Chronological statement of his activite
  - a) Forms for Manufacturing department- Anritsn Electric Co. Lmt. (Box 21)
  - b) Same, for Tokyo Keiki Co. Lmt.
  - c) Same, for Niigata Iron Works Lmt.
  - d) Miscellaneous notebook-biological, industrial journals
  - e) Book on “Scientific Management Material Developed From the Large and Extensive Consulting Practice of Carl. G. Barth and Made Available to the Graduate School of Business Through the Courtesy of Carl G. Barth and King Hathaway, December 1937”
  - Larger volume with same title (Box 22)
  - Looseleaf binder; photostated articles and reports by Hathaway (Box 23)